Do you want subtitles for any video?
-=[ ai.OpenSubtitles.com ]=-
Previously on
Star Trek: Strange New Worlds...
PIKE:
T'quiel Dawn.
- UNA: You know their names.
- PIKE: Muliq Al Alcazar.
[shouting]
We can keep doing this.
but we can also talk about it.
It's classified.
UNA:
How do you know you can't make
a different choice?
Yuuto Hoshide.
One that saves all of you?
PIKE:
Andrea Lopez.
I accepted my fate.
PIKE:
It goes beyond my own life.
What if your fate
is what you make it?
PIKE:
Maybe that's the good
in-in seeing my future.
Stay the course.
save their lives.
PIKE:
Captain's log. stardate 1457.9.
The Enterprise is on the edge
of the Neutral Zone.
A narrow band of space
separating the Romulan Empire
from the Federation.
A remnant of a treaty
from 100 years ago.
when a destructive war was waged
between our two cultures.
Enterprise and the USS Cayuga
are here to help the outposts
that guard the Neutral Zone
with much needed
retrofitting and supplies.
We already had spaghetti
last night.
I'm making pasta mama.
Just add eggs. parmesan...
...lightly sauté and it
transforms from leftovers
- into something new.
- Mm.
Little like what we're doing
to these outposts.
Not as tasty. though.
Keep hearing rumors the Romulans
are developing new weapons.
Ah. the Romulans
are the bogeymen.
No one's ever seen one.
Nobody even knows
what they look like.
and yet they get blamed
for a lot of things around here.
Some actually their fault.
You know.
I think I miss the beard.
Yeah. I...
It felt like it belonged
to a different era of captain.
Thought that's what you were
going for: man out of time.
How have you been holding up?
Someone told me
I have better places to be.
so I'm trying to be there.
Better places.
And how's that going?
You tell me.
[chuckles]
Well.
Much as I love you
being mysterious.
I've got a date on the far side
of the Neutral Zone.
Mmm.
Anyone I know?
Not that kind of date. actually.
You know. I'm making osso bucco
next week. if you're interested.
I mean. I'm always curious
who the Chris of tomorrow
is gonna be.
Beard. no beard.
Surprise me.
[chuckles]
[door whooshes open]
AL-SALAH:
We are on our own out here.
How do you plan to fix
our supply chain problems?
Under the proposed
retrofit directive.
every outpost will be equipped
with state-of-the-art
matter synthesizers
fueled by minerals
from the asteroid itself.
They will also
each receive a set
of fully-automated mining craft
that can be operated remotely.
Commander?
How does this sound?
Sounds like what I've been
asking for
for the last five years.
- [chuckles] Well. you're welcome.
- [door whooshes open]
You know I'm working.
I just wanted to meet
Captain Pike.
[chuckles] Apologies.
Maat has always dreamed about
joining Starfleet.
W-What did you say your name is?
Maat.
Maat Al-Salah.
AL-SALAH [echoing]:
He has a model of
the Enterprise back home.
You're quite a hero of his.
MAAT:
Is it true you can tell
what warp you're at
just by listening
- to the sound of the engine?
- [people shouting]
[echoing stops]
Apologies. I-I think
I need a moment.
- I'm sorry. he just gets a little excited.
- It's totally fine.
I'm just feeling a little
under the weather.
Number One and Spock can answer
any further questions you have.
[door whooshes open]
[muffled. indistinct voices]
UNA:
Captain.
[people shouting]
Chris. that boy.
He's one of the names
you mentioned.
Yes. I wasn't expecting that.
There's two cadets
who don't make it.
He's one of them.
You don't have
to face this alone.
What are you going to do?
I don't know.
But I have
to do something. don't I?
[door whooshes open]
Computer.
Take dictation.
Dear Maat...
...I'm gratified to see
your deep interest in Starfleet.
and I encourage you
to pursue your dream.
but there is something
you should know about...
...the future?
MAN:
You'll figure out how to say it.
Trust me.
Who the hell are you?
Thought that
would've been obvious.
I'm you.
PIKE:
Space.
The final frontier.
These are the voyages
of the starship Enterprise.
Its five-year mission:
to explore strange new worlds...
...to seek out new life
and new civilizations.
to boldly go
where no one has gone before.
♪
Sorry.
It's just. this room brings back
a lot of memories.
Is this some kind of...
Joke? No.
How am I supposed to believe...
That I'm really you?
You ever gonna let me
get a word in edgewise?
I knew you were going
to say that.
Does that help?
I've been doing this long enough
that I'm not just gonna
take the word of somebody
who shows up in my cabin
and says he's future me.
Mm.
Your first pony was named
Sir Neighs-a-Lot.
He broke his leg
in a rainstorm. Your parents
had to put him down.
and you cried for a week.
Ever tell anybody that?
It's hard when your tragic
backstory starts with...
A silly name.
Sorry.
Look...
I'm here because that letter
you're about to write
is going to wreck the future.
How. though?
Wh...
W-Why?
Two cadets die in that accident
seven years from now.
Maat is one of them.
You're trying to figure out
how to save the cadets
and yourself.
And you do.
We do.
You write to all of them.
tell them
not to be there that day.
But like so much of this
time-bending stuff.
there are. uh...
...unforeseen consequences.
Well. how bad can it be
if I figure out a way to save
all the cadets and myself?
Hell. isn't you standing here
evidence that I pull it off?
Yes.
And that's the problem.
Causality is complex.
The letter is just
the first domino
to fall in a chain reaction
of events
that leads to
catastrophic results.
It alters the future
in ways that we never
intended to change.
You sound like one of those
Klingon monks from Boreth.
Who do you think sent me?
They gave me
something to show you.
Is that what I think it is?
A time crystal.
It will show you the effects
of changing your fate.
This is serious.
This is
"end of the world" stuff.
I know that you would never
put your own fate
before the fate of the galaxy.
And that's how
I convinced the Klingons
to let me show you instead.
Instead of what?
You know the Klingons.
Nothing they wouldn't rather
solve with a bat'leth.
Hi...
Captain?
Uh. sorry.
Wh-What was I saying?
Um. that since
the age of wooden ships.
all shipmasters
have had a happy
privilege of...
Right.
Um. I assume I was-I was
talking about weddings?
Yeah?
Which we get to perform.
as captains
on-on ships.
So...
We take you...
...and-and you... uh...
A-and you...
...both want to get married.
- So...
- [alarm blaring]
COMPUTER:
All decks. red alert.
Repeat. all decks. red alert.
Thank God.
SPOCK:
Number One to Captain Pike.
Outpost Four reports
they are under attack
by a space vessel.
identity unknown.
Copy. Mr. Spock.
On my way.
[boatswain's whistle blows]
What's the situation. Mr. Spock?
Lieutenant Uhura can brief you.
Outpost Four reported
under attack. sir.
Then message terminates.
Any word from Two or Three?
Two has not responded
to our hails.
And Three has also gone silent.
How far out are we. Erica?
Eight minutes from Outpost Four
at this velocity. sir.
Did Outpost Four say anything
else about the attacking vessel?
No identification. sir.
ORTEGAS:
I'm guessing it's the same
attackers. sir.
The Romulans.
Let's not make guesses just yet.
I'd like to avoid a war
if I can.
Maintain course. Alert me
when we're two minutes out.
Mr. Spock. could you join me
in the ready room. please.
2266.
Seven years into the future.
I do not understand.
Is this one of your human jokes?
I'm serious. Spock. This is...
Well. it's time crystal stuff.
Approaching this logically.
time travel seems
a less likely solution
than that you are
compromised mentally.
And as your first officer.
in these circumstances.
it is my job to assume command.
I agree. If I was
mentally compromised.
But I am not.
So. what's the logical solution?
Perhaps the doctor
could do a full scan.
Why don't we try a mind meld?
That way you'll know
if I'm lying or not.
My mind to your mind.
My thoughts to your thoughts.
[screaming]
You...
carry the weight
of a terrible future. Chris.
The accident in question
was six months ago.
In this timeline.
there were no cadets
at the reactor incident to save.
No one was even hurt.
I need your help. Spock.
I was sent forward to this
moment in time for a reason.
We have to figure out why.
I would posit
that in this present.
you were never injured
in the training accident.
thus. you remained captain
of the Enterprise.
putting you in charge
at a crucial moment
in the ship's existence.
A moment where the whole future
hangs in the balance.
All we can surmise
is that. in the prime future.
some other captain
of the Enterprise
must have commanded it differently.
Thus. it is imperative
you do not change
what you would normally do
on the ship.
I thought we were trying
to avoid a terrible future.
We are trying to discover
why this future is.
in the estimation
of your older self. worse...
So the only way to discover
the terrible future...
...is to live it.
ORTEGAS:
Enterprise is in position
and holding. sir.
Just out of weapons range.
Detecting a fair amount
of debris. but no sign
of any attacking ship.
Let's triple check.
Nyota. see if there are
any other Federation ships
in the vicinity.
in case we need backup.
The Farragut is closest.
A couple hours away.
That's La'An's ship. sir.
Yes. I'd forgotten.
Sir. we're being hailed.
It's the outpost. Audio only.
AL-SALAH:
Enterprise. can you read me?
This is Commander
Hansen Al-Salah.
This is Pike.
What's your status?
Outposts Two. Three
and Eight are gone.
Unknown weapon
completely destroyed.
We had our deflector shields
on maximum.
Hit by enormous power.
First attack
blew through our shields.
If they hit us again
with our deflectors gone...
Do you read me. Enterprise?
What hit you. Commander?
What vessel? Can you identify?
Negative.
It all happened so fast.
And it seems to have
disappeared somehow.
Switching to visual.
Enterprise. can you see?
My command post here...
we're a mile deep.
on an asteroid.
- [alarm blaring]
- almost solid iron.
and even through
our deflectors. it did this.
Can you see?
We see. Hansen.
Was your son with you?
No. thank God.
What can you tell us
about the attacker?
No identity.
Only a glimpse of...
Then it fired something at us.
High-energy plasma.
Fantastic power.
Vessel seems to have disappeared.
but it is out there somewhere.
[panting]
Enterprise.
there's something's
on our sensors moving fast.
Send us your signal.
Switching.
Enterprise. can you see.
in the center of my screen?
- Phasers?
- Still out of range. sir.
We're out of range. Commander.
Do you have weapons?
Negative. Phasers gone.
Weapon crew are all dead.
Hail them. Warn that ship off.
I'm trying.
They're not acknowledging us.
Aah!
Interesting how they became
visible for just a moment.
Perhaps necessary
to use weapons.
Sir. We have to find a way
to engage them.
We need something
to follow. Lieutenant.
We have no visuals.
Analyzing their movement
patterns now.
Give me a moment.
Sir? Incoming warp signature.
We're being hailed.
It's one of ours. The Farragut.
La'An's ship?
- Who's hailing us?
- UHURA: Their captain.
James Kirk.
Sam's brother?
Uh... I mean. uh...
On screen.
Enterprise. this is
Captain James T. Kirk
of the USS Farragut.
offering assistance.
Christopher Pike.
Good to see you. Captain.
We received Outpost Four's
distress signal
and pushed warp nine
for as long as we safely could.
Do we know who did this?
We have a pretty good idea.
We're trying to determine. conclusively.
I may have a lead. sir.
The ship in question
appears to have
a kind of cloaking device.
But they still have a detectable
gravitational presence.
So. can we track it.
Commander...?
Spock.
Theoretically. yes.
By detecting the microlensing
of background stars
we can determine
an approximate location.
Impressive. Mr. Spock.
Where's the intruder now?
He has changed heading.
At a very leisurely maneuver.
- They may not be aware of us.
- How can that be true?
They had to decloak to fire.
Their device may work both ways:
it makes them invisible
to our sensors.
but requires
a massive amount of energy.
They are likely flying blind.
without enough power
to run their scanners.
So. we can't see them
but they can't see us.
His heading is now
1-1-1. mark 1-4.
The exact heading
a Romulan vessel would take
toward the Neutral Zone
and home.
Sir. it's the Romulans.
We have to take them out.
We can't enter the Neutral Zone.
Starfleet is clear on this.
We do. that's considered
an act of war.
They've destroyed
three of our outposts.
That's not an act of war?
We attack the Romulans
without authorization.
the Federation
will consider us expendable.
KIRK:
We do have another option.
We can shadow the ship.
Follow a parallel course.
to buy us some time.
- Not an intercept course. sir?
- No.
The captain is right.
That would be
a declaration of war.
But if Enterprise and Farragut
match course and speed
with the enemy ship. exactly.
move for move.
they might think
we're just a reflection.
Echoes on their sensors.
That way we won't lose them
while we wait to hear back
from Starfleet.
Let's start shadowing them.
Uhura. send a message
to Starfleet.
Ask for permission
to engage the Romulans.
Captain Kirk. we'll be talking.
I look forward to it. Kirk out.
Get Sam Kirk up here. ASAP.
Am I off the record here. sir?
Jim was always
at the top of his class.
He's smart and highly
skilled. obviously.
but he's not above
relying on charm
or even luck.
Sounds like a wild card.
A whole deck of 'em.
He doesn't like to take the path
everyone else does.
And he doesn't like to lose.
Should we be worried that
he's going to start a war?
Look. I'm not gonna say that
Jim isn't a pain in the ass.
He is.
He's a huge pain in the ass.
But the truth is.
he's as fine a captain
as Starfleet has.
- Okay. Good to know.
- Like I said.
he does like
to bend the rules sometimes.
No. more like all the time.
SPOCK:
Captain. can you come
to the bridge?
There is something
you should see.
UHURA:
There's a comet ahead.
and its trail
is reflecting a signal
on an unused EM frequency.
It is encoded.
Mr. Spock is trying to decipher.
But we think it might
be from the enemy ship.
They cut off transmission.
but we managed to make a copy.
I think it's the feed
from their bridge. sir.
So. we're finally going to see
what the Romulans look like.
Put it on screen.
please. Mr. Spock.
♪
PIKE:
Captain Kirk.
welcome aboard the Enterprise.
Thanks. Captain Pike.
Sam.
Quite the ship you got here.
He's jealous.
[chuckling]
Well. we're not gonna
get out of this problem
by not talking about it.
Agreed.
I'd like to hear what Mr. Spock
has to say for himself.
I assure you. Lieutenant.
the similarities between
Vulcans and Romulans
came as a surprise to me.
Perhaps even more so than you.
It does seem suspicious.
Not the similarity itself.
but that we should
discover it right now.
What are you suggesting?
Well. it's no secret
that the Vulcans and the humans
are in alliance.
Perhaps the Romulans allowed us
to see that transmission
in hopes that it would
sow discord
- among us.
- ORTEGAS: Even if we ignore
the pointy-eared elephant
in the room.
we have another problem
to worry about.
We're going to lose our prey.
MITCHELL:
The Romulans are on a bearing
to return to the Neutral Zone
in an hour.
KIRK:
I don't think we can wait.
We have to make a choice here.
SPOCK:
Say we do make that choice.
Their plasma weapon
can still slice through
our shields.
That. in conjunction
with their cloaking device.
gives them a tactical advantage.
Even against our ships
working in tandem.
M'BENGA:
Working in tandem for what?
To destroy them?
Say we're lucky
enough to do that.
Isn't that. technically.
an act of war?
ORTEGAS:
I hate to say it. Doc.
but they started it.
This isn't a schoolyard.
Billions of lives
are at stake here.
Which is why I want to hear
everyone's opinion
before we take any action.
- I vote against war.
- ORTEGAS: So do I.
I just think that means
killing Romulans.
Captain. your thoughts?
What happens when
they return to Romulus
and tell their leaders
that the Federation
won't even fight back?
I'm starting to lean
toward attack.
If we allow them to destroy our
outposts with no repercussions.
we run the risk of war.
Have to believe
there's another way forward.
I think we should attack.
Mr. Spock?
SPOCK:
If the Romulans
are an offshoot
of my Vulcan blood.
which I believe.
then attack is indeed
the only option.
Vulcan. like Earth.
had its aggressive
colonizing period.
Savage. even by human standards.
If the Romulans retain
this martial philosophy.
then weakness is something
we dare not show.
ORTEGAS:
Well.
if Spock and I can agree.
then there's hope for all of us.
We don't all agree.
KIRK:
Hold a moment. Captain Pike.
that comet we're approaching
might just be the alternative
that you've been looking for.
Mr. Spock. can you put up the
trajectory on screen. please?
Currently. the Romulan ship
is headed for the comet's tail.
Now. I know
that they're invisible
and we can't lock on
to their exact position.
But the second
they go through that.
particle distortion
will reveal their location.
And we'll be flanking them
on either side.
They'll be pendent and we'll be
able to get weapons locked.
Good plan. Captain.
Captain's personal log.
stardate 1709.2.
Per Captain Kirk's plan.
we are mounting a pincer move.
Our two ships
will slowly drift closer
as the Romulans remain unaware.
When they pass through
the comet's tail
giving us their exact location.
we will be in weapons range.
Kirk. however.
has agreed to my plan
to neutralize. not destroy.
the Bird-of-Prey.
leaving open
the possibility of dialogue.
And yet I remain concerned
this brash. young Starfleet
captain follows his own rules.
I can't help but wonder.
is Kirk the reason
I was sent here?
If I wasn't here to stop him.
would we be lead into a war?
Ortegas. maintain
present course. but be ready.
I'll keep my foot over
the gas. just in case.
SPOCK:
Still tracking
the gravitational presence
of the Romulans.
Their trajectory
remains unchanged.
Holding position.
Let us know when you see them.
Enterprise.
We're passing through the tail.
Any second now.
[indistinct chatter over comm]
Something isn't right.
The captain is correct.
We should have seen them by now.
KIRK:
Enterprise.
I don't like this.
SPOCK:
Reading gravitational
signature again.
It's behind the Farragut.
- Kirk. get out of there!
- Red Alert!
Red Alert.
Erica. close that distance
as fast as you can.
Attack pattern Tiberius 4.
Get behind them.
Fire!
[grunting]
[alarms blaring]
Fire phasers. Captain.
We're out of range. We're just
as likely to hit you as them.
Maybe you'll draw their fire.
Mitchell. full phasers. now.
Holy...
We actually clipped them.
Nice shooting. Jenna.
Nyota. hail them.
I want them focused on us.
Hailing. sir.
Keep firing.
MITCHELL:
They're firing
their plasma weapon.
Brace for impact!
Damage to Decks Six.
Seven. and Nine.
And weapon control is down.
That should have destroyed us.
How are we still standing?
SPOCK:
They were shooting
at a distance.
Perhaps their plasma weapon
is less effective
when fired long range.
Status of the Farragut?
Critical.
They will lose life support
inside of five minutes.
I can get us there
in 30 seconds.
Pike to transporter.
Get the pads warmed up. Chief.
We're about to test
their upper limits.
Clear the pads. There's
one more group behind us.
[sighs] Am I glad to see you.
Oh. um...
I didn't know you were
a hugger. Lieutenant.
Oh. Commander.
Or have you forgotten?
I d...
Of course I haven't.
Uh. uh. speaking of...
when's the last time
you've talked to Una?
Well. I-I can't talk to her.
No one can. It...
She's not allowed contact.
Of course.
[trilling]
KIRK:
Captain Pike.
We need to talk. Now.
You flinched.
You deliberated and we lost.
We fired. Captain.
And we were fired upon.
That's why you're still here.
From the start.
you wanted to cripple them.
not take them out.
We may have different
points of view.
but do not question
my combat readiness. Captain.
I'm saying caution means
you're not going to put
everything you have
into the punch.
And that's a good way to lose.
because your enemy will see that
and act accordingly.
All this because
of a second's delay?
Tell me I'm wrong. Captain.
and I will back down.
If you're saying
you're more willing
to take risks than I am.
I don't disagree.
And let me remind you that
you're saying that on my ship.
after yours has been destroyed.
Fair.
I'm just saying
I underestimated him.
I'm not going to do it again.
SPOCK:
Captains Pike and Kirk
to the bridge.
There is something
you'll both want to see.
[door whooshes open]
Before they cloaked. I was able
to scan the Bird-of-Prey.
They are trailing
trilithium fragments.
Their power supply is damaged.
I do not believe
they have enough
to make it back to Romulus.
- Do we know their position?
- Yes.
On a heading
for the Neutral Zone.
We could overtake them.
What's the status
of our weapons?
Our offensive capabilities
are limited.
Phasers are down.
And torpedo launch tubes
sustained damage in the attack.
But the Romulans
don't know that.
They will if we pull up
on their six and can't fire.
Lieutenant Uhura. open
a channel to the Romulan ship.
Sir? They haven't responded
to any of our hails before.
I know. Open a channel.
We're going to
send them a message.
What are you doing?
Taking a risk.
This is Captain Christopher Pike
of the USS Enterprise.
Our two cultures have been
at war for 100 years.
Long enough that
we don't even question it.
But I believe we can
make another choice.
Right now.
I'm offering you
a temporary cease-fire.
so that we can talk.
For the first time in 100 years.
Okay. That was... unexpected.
They want to destroy us.
but they also want to get home.
Knowing what your opponent wants
is key to a successful negotiation.
That's assuming
they can be negotiated with.
Captain Pike.
the Romulans are calling.
Looks like we're about
to find out.
On screen. please. Nyota.
Captain Pike.
it is good to make
your acquaintance.
Commander.
I know your ships
attacked our outposts
on the edge of the Neutral Zone.
But I also know
that our two cultures
have been at war for generations
without ever having been
face-to-face.
I don't know why
your ancestors attacked Earth
or what my ancestors did
in retaliation.
I only know that
we're paying a bill
that was written long before
you and I were ever born.
Perhaps it's time
we reconsider the cost.
So. we can blow each other
out of the sky
using what little power
we have left.
or we can try
something different.
We can explain ourselves
to each other.
Understand each other.
Empathize.
If we don't. this war between us
will simply continue. unabated.
And the cost for that is sure.
Death.
More and more death.
Our peoples are indeed
different. Captain.
In our culture. your words
are a show of weakness.
What chance does dialogue offer.
save to delay me?
Why should I listen to you?
PIKE:
Both our ships are damaged.
Your cloak
is unstable. which leaves you
vulnerable to our weapons.
Maybe you have
enough power to attack us.
Maybe you have enough power
to get back to Romulus
without repairs.
Conversely.
maybe we can marshal
our weapons and destroy you
before you make it
to the Neutral Zone.
Or perhaps we chase you
across the border
and destroy you and get out
before anyone's the wiser.
So what is it that
you're suggesting. Captain?
A good faith gesture.
Two hours.
Enough time to repair
our ships and bury the dead.
And maybe this bit of mercy
will lead to something
further and better
between our two cultures.
Two hours.
Captain.
They are lying.
Romulans can't be trusted.
They shot Farragut
right in front of us.
Stand down. Erica.
You can't let them
get away with it!
Stand down!
Yes. sir.
Sensor readings suggest
the Romulans have stopped
forward movement.
I wonder what they're doing
over there.
Hopefully...
...same thing we are.
SUBCOMMANDER:
A cease-fire?
This is Federation weakness.
Is it not the Romulan way
to attack when we are given
advantage like this?
We are engaged in a cease-fire.
Subcommander.
We have two hours.
Put all hands
to repair our engines.
If we do not. we will not
make it back to Romulus.
Sir. we should commit all hands
to weapons repair.
The Federation
has given us the advantage.
We can strike before
this ridiculous cease-fire
is completed.
This is your fourth mission.
is it not. Subcommander?
Third. sir.
I served with your Uncle Tarqan
during the Reman campaign.
did you know that. Subcommander?
I did.
His death was
a great victory for Romulus.
Yes. he was brave.
His commander. however.
was a fool.
He forced him to fight
after we'd lost weapons.
and the only
logical choice was retreat.
He did not have to die.
Sir?
His death was a waste.
And it was stupid.
It left us weaker.
Now. I can say that
because I'm old enough
and I don't care
what people think of me.
Pride is not something
we can afford.
We look at the world
clearly on my ship.
We do not make choices
based on ego.
Engines first.
Then. weapons. That is my order.
Or are you so arrogant
you think you know better
than your Commander?
No. sir.
Good.
Because I need you.
I don't know if this peace game
we're playing with
the Federation will work.
But I have to see it through.
And if we achieve it.
then. good.
But if not?
Then you'll get your war.
Do you want some coffee?
I do not drink coffee.
I do drink tea.
All right.
Would you like some tea?
No. thank you. Captain.
[chuckling]
Well. the more things change.
the more they stay the same.
It's good to see you're
still you. Spock.
So many things
have gone wrong today.
[sighs]
The loss of Outpost Four.
The destruction of the Farragut.
Any one of them could set us
on a path to a dark future.
But I can't help feeling...
...that there's something
worse to come.
Typically. no one can know
the future in the moment.
One can only follow
one's instincts
and hope the truth
will present itself.
Spock...
...what happened to Una?
She was sentenced to
the Federation penal colony
on Salius Six.
where she has spent
much of the last seven years.
Why?
Her deception.
I am confused.
Even years ago.
I thought you knew.
- [door chimes]
- Come.
SPOCK:
If you'll excuse me.
I wish to supervise
the repair of the phaser
array personally.
Captain.
[door whooshes shut]
I know you want me
to change tack. but
pride is just not something
we can afford.
You want me to tell you
that I wouldn't have tried
to blow those Romulans
out of the sky?
Well. I would have.
But it wasn't my call.
Okay. We're here. now.
And the truth is...
I don't know these Romulans
can't be trusted.
But I also don't know
if they can.
And neither do you.
Fair enough.
I'd like to explore
a backup plan.
If you'll give me the resources.
I'm listening.
Look. the Romulans
just bought themselves
some time.
Sure. they can use that time
to make repairs.
But remember. they're on
the edge of the Neutral Zone.
They could also use it
to call for reinforcements.
So.
what if we did the same?
Just in case they decide
to turn and fight after all.
Jim. we're on the far edge
of Federation space.
It takes days
to get a message to Starfleet.
We're weeks away
from help getting to us.
even at maximum warp.
But the Romulans
don't know that.
Captain Kirk...
...what are you suggesting?
Captain Pike...
...can I borrow a shuttle?
Try it now.
ENGINEER [Scottish accent]:
Aye. that's the one.
This is where the auto repair
was getting hung up.
She's very fused.
I do not need to remind you
that we have less than two hours
to restore phaser control
to working order.
ENGINEER:
I'm an engineer.
not a miracle worker.
Mr. Spock.
Two minutes. Captain.
Status?
MITCHELL:
We have engines.
but weapons systems
are not back online.
Bridge to Spock. Status?
Working on it. Captain.
Working on it.
UHURA:
Two hours. Captain.
And... mark.
Open a channel
to the Romulan ship.
Have you repaired
your ship. Commander?
yours. Captain?
Conventional wisdom suggests
that our next move
is to resume hostilities.
To fight.
You yourself told me
that in your culture
to do anything else
would be a sign of weakness.
But let me tell you a way
in which humans are not weak.
Our strength comes from our
willingness to see a partner
instead of an enemy.
In our culture. that is an act
of faith and strength.
not a failure of character.
Do Romulans have
that kind of strength?
I too tire of endless war.
[intermittent beeping]
[alarm blaring]
Why is the fleet here?
I did not call for them.
I alerted them
of our situation. Commander.
The Federation showed weakness.
It is the Romulan way to strike.
You were not going to.
I took matters
into my own hands.
You disobeyed a direct order.
Had you not negotiated
with the Federation.
I would not have needed to.
We undertook
this mission to test
the strength of the Federation.
They showed us they lack it.
We should have destroyed them
- the moment they did.
- You don't remember
a time without war.
But I do.
Who wins an endless war
with the Federation?
We will. Commander.
An endless war.
by definition. can never be won.
Captain Pike
will not trust my word now.
What does that matter?
He will be dead soon.
[scoffs]
Take him off the bridge.
UHURA:
We're being hailed. sir.
It's the Romulan flagship.
On screen.
Human.
I am here to accept
your unconditional surrender.
Nice to meet you. too.
I'm Captain Pike
of the Federation
Starship Enterprise.
And you are?
You may address me as Praetor.
It is customary to kneel.
As I'm not a Romulan.
you'll forgive me if I don't.
Now. I'm confused.
We are holding to our side
of the Neutral Zone. as you are.
Yet you demand our surrender?
Captain. I have you surrounded.
Surrender
or we will destroy you.
You have one minute to comply.
You know. I don't like her.
Perimeter alert.
We have ships incoming. sir. Dozens.
- More Romulans?
- No.
They look like... ours.
I've got a secure channel
from the lead ship. sir.
It's Captain Kirk.
Chris. the reinforcements
you ordered?
Been 100 years
since the Federation
has seen the Romulans.
We didn't know what
their ships looked like.
and so I figured they don't know
what ours look like. either.
All robotic mining craft?
Mining. hauling.
Not one of them manned.
But to the Romulans.
who's to say we aren't
a Federation armada?
You sneaky son of a bitch.
It's enough
to bluff with. I hope.
Try not to get us
in a real fight.
I'll do my best.
Thanks. Captain.
It's my pleasure. Captain.
Bridge to Spock.
We really could use
some phasers right about now.
How's it going down there?
We are making progress.
The conduits
are severely damaged.
Work faster. Mr. Spock.
We're going to need weapons soon
or we're not
going to need them at all.
Romulan praetor
is hailing us. sir.
Keep a secure channel open
for Captain Kirk
so he can listen in.
You ready to sell this?
Ready as I'll ever be.
By now you've probably noticed
our armada of Starfleet
Delta Class attack ships.
But we won't have to use them.
will we. Praetor?
This is an act
of unparalleled aggression
on the border
of our territory. Captain.
No. just a standard
training maneuver
that happened to land our fleet
here the same time as yours.
You want to know
what actually is
an act of unparalleled
aggression?
A Romulan Bird-of-Prey
using cloaking technology
destroying our
Neutral Zone outposts.
I know nothing
of what you speak.
That's okay.
We'll send you a recording
of it de-cloaking
right before destroying
Outpost Four.
[explosion on recording]
PRAETOR:
I see.
Romulan ship is de-cloaking
and breaking formation.
Heading our way.
Praetor. what is this?
This is a culling. Captain.
That commander should not have
allowed himself to be caught.
ORTEGAS:
Sir.
It's the Bird-of-Prey
we've been chasing.
Nyota. pause communication.
Open a channel
with the Romulan Commander.
[comm chimes]
Captain.
So. we see each other
once again. after all.
What are you doing?
Only what is asked of me.
I never called for that Armada.
We can beam you
and your crew aboard.
You don't have to do this.
It is not our way.
I regret that we meet
in this way.
You and I are of a kind.
In a different reality.
I could've called you friend.
What purpose
will it serve to die?
We are creatures of duty.
you and I.
Just one more duty to perform.
Do not be upset.
I have accepted my fate.
Perhaps. someday.
my sacrifice will lead
to an end to this
conflict between us.
They're powering up weapons.
The Romulan praetor
is hailing us again. sir.
On screen.
Our fleet is stronger now.
And I am ready to accept
your surrender.
This is really how you want
to end 100 years of peace?
What do Romulans care of peace?
It means nothing to us.
And your apparent affinity
for it has sealed your fate.
Thank you. Captain Pike.
If not for your weakness.
we would never have known
what easy targets
your Federation would be.
Goodbye.
They're powering up
weapons again.
Evasive maneuvers. Erica.
Pattern Zeta-3.
Kirk. get back here.
We're about to warp out.
Roger that.
Captain. warp engines
aren't engaging.
Erica...
I'm sorry. sir.
MITCHELL:
Sir. the drone ships are moving.
Son of a bitch.
Kirk. what are you doing?
Covering your escape.
Get those engines fixed.
ORTEGAS:
He's putting the drones
between us and the Romulans.
[grunting]
MITCHELL:
Captain Kirk has
beamed on board.
Engines online. Captain.
Hit it.
Damage report.
MITCHELL:
Reports coming from all decks.
Captain.
the Romulans are broadcasting
on all known
subspace frequencies.
It's declaration of war. sir.
Against the Federation.
MITCHELL:
Decks Five 11. 12. and 22 are
all reporting hull breaches.
Weapons systems
took a direct hit.
Spock.
Medical.
♪
Massive cerebral trauma.
Major blood loss.
Spinal fractures.
Radiation burns across
40% of his body.
I'm not sure that
he will recover from this.
But if he does...
...he will not be the same.
♪
FUTURE PIKE:
I know what you're thinking.
I was thinking the same thing
when I went through this.
That I traded
my fate for Spock's?
Yes.
This isn't going to help. but...
...it gets worse.
This war with the Romulans.
Millions die.
So far. It's still going on.
Not only did you start something
that should never
have been started.
The best chance
at a lasting peace
between the Federation and
the Romulans in any timeline?
Well...
turns out he's lying
in a biobed.
We all want to think
our future is important.
And ours... yours and mine...
it is.
Just not the way you think.
Time is. uh.
is complicated.
But the monks showed me
something simple.
Every time we change the path.
he dies.
And he's got things to do.
Fate-of-the-galaxy type things.
Paths diverge.
But I am the result of one
that should never
have been taken.
- Thank you.
- Hey.
look at it this way.
How many people get to
give their life for someone
twice in one day?
See? Twice. 'cause there's
two of us and we're both...
Yeah. I-I got it.
Got it.
[door chimes]
[soft chuckle]
Oh. yeah.
Come.
Not interrupting. am I?
No. I...
Not really. I'm just. uh...
...talking to myself.
Fancy a drink?
Sure.
You know. uh...
I don't think
I can explain it. but...
...I think I was
supposed to meet you.
I get that feeling too.
I. uh. honestly just came by
to check on you.
I'm sorry things went down
the way they did.
You tried for something better.
Tried and lost.
Did it ever occur to you
that sometimes
you can't avoid a fight?
If you had just
chased that Romulan ship
from the get-go
and taken it out.
maybe none of this
would've happened.
You're a good captain. Jim Kirk.
Enterprise would be lucky
to have you.
You thinking of retiring?
[chuckles]: No.
Oh. no. No. not yet.
So...
come on over
and have a seat. Captain.
Tell me about yourself.
Where are you from?
[sighs]
I grew up in Iowa.
[fading]: My father George
was first officer
on the Kelvin
before he moved to...
♪
Computer.
delete file.
[door chimes]
Come.
SPOCK:
Captain.
- Am I interrupting?
- No.
I'm very glad to see you.
But you saw me only moments ago.
Right.
You left the briefing suddenly.
It was uncharacteristic.
Was it?
But now your demeanor
appears changed.
Having heard the boy's name.
I cannot help but wonder
if this pertains to your future.
Let's just say I...
think the universe is telling me
that some fates are inescapable.
And even if I could
get out of mine...
...it might just
fall to someone else.
Someone you know?
Yes.
Is that why you are
very glad to see me?
I believe I may owe you
a debt of gratitude. Captain.
Although for precisely what.
I do not know.
Spock. you are...
You are very important to me.
As you are to me. Captain.
Chris.
["Makin' Memories"
by Melissa Carper playing]
[door whooshes shut]
♪ I'm makin' memories...♪
[boatswain's whistle blows]
♪ I'd like to remember♪
♪ I'm meetin' new people♪
♪ I'd like to recall♪
♪ Some of their names♪
♪ Like Larry and Steve♪
♪ Yeah. I'm makin' memories♪
♪ That I can keep♪
♪ Tonight I'm makin' memories♪
♪ I'd like to remember♪
♪ I'm meetin' new people♪
♪ I'd like to recall♪
♪ I'm makin' memories♪
♪ I'd like to keep♪
♪ Yeah. I'm makin' memories♪
- ♪ I'd sure like to keep.♪
- Captain.
incoming message
from Starfleet Command.
Captain Batel
is beaming onboard.
They want you
and Commander Chin-Riley
to meet her
in the transporter room.
Captain Batel.
I didn't think we'll be
seeing each other so soon.
I know. Captain.
And for the record.
I'm sorry about this.
Wh...
What the hell is going on?
Under Starfleet
code of conduct 587.63.
I'm arresting Commander
Una Chin-Riley for violations
of our anti-genetic
modification directive.
She's an Illyrian. Chris.
I don't care what she is.
- She's my...
- I don't like it either.
but I have orders.
[grunts]
Captain.
Don't.
I've known this might happen
for years.
I didn't ask for this job.
I really am sorry.
So am I.
Because this isn't over.
BATEL:
Energize.
Captioning sponsored by CBS
Captioned by
Media Access Group at WGBH access.wgbh.org
Support us and become VIP member
to remove all ads from www.OpenSubtitles.org